Finding Aid for William F. Sutter papers, 1950-1954, 2008
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William F. Sutter papers 1950-1954, 2008 1950-1954
Sutter, William F.
1.0 linear feet
2014117 Aa 2
Student at the University of Michigan Medical School, 1950-1954 from Crystal Falls, Michigan. Lecture notes and course material from his medical classes and a written recollection of his memories as a medical student.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Received from the family in April 2008 (donor no. 10038 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
William Frederick Sutter was born in Crystal Falls, Michigan on October 6, 1927. He was the third of three sons born to John A. and Clara Moline Sutter. The Sutter family owned and operated the Crystal Falls Dairy where he began working at a young age. Sutter graduated from Crystal Falls High School in 1945 where he excelled in math and science. Following high school graduation, he spent a year sailing on freighters for the Cleveland Cliffs Company followed by a stint in the Merchant Marine before enrolling in Northern Michigan University. Sutter graduated from Northern Michigan with a B.S. degree in 1950.
Sutter applied to the University of Michigan Medical School and was accepted in the fall of 1950. He graduated with an M.D. degree from Michigan in 1954. Following graduation he was drafted into the United States Army with the rank of Captain. He served at Brook Army Hospital in San Antonio, Texas and Fort Sill, Oklahoma. After completing his military service, Sutter returned to Michigan to fill the medical practice of Dr. Leo Goulet in Ludington. Sutter remained at the practice in Ludington for 43 years, serving patients until he retired from private practice at the age of 74.
While specializing in family practice Sutter also worked in occupational medicine. He was an examining surgeon for the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad and also provided services to Strait Steel and Wire and the City of Ludington. He served as Medical Director of the Oakview Medical Care Facility from 1983 until 2008. In 2004 he received a State of Michigan Special Tribute recognizing his 50 years of medical service provided to resident of Michigan.
Sutter married Barbara Ray on June 19, 1954 in Ann Arbor, Michigan. They had four children, Pam, Susan, Laura, and Eric. William Sutter died on May 22, 2008.
The William F. Sutter papers document his medical education at the University of Michigan from 1950 to 1954 and include lecture notes and course material. Sutter wrote a brief recollection in 2008 regarding his recollections as a medical student. The papers are organized into two series: Biographical and Medical School Course Material
Subjects:
Sutter, William F.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Student notebooks.; persname; geogname
Subjects - Visual Materials:
corpname; persname; geogname
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
corpname; persname; geogname
Contributors:
corpname; persname; geogname
Genre Terms:
genre
- Biographical
  The Biographical series includes Sutter's two-page recollection of his time as a medical student and a copy of his obituary from 2008.
  - Biographical, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Recollections of Medical School, 2008 (Box 1)
- Medical School Course Material
  Medical School Course Material consists of Sutter's lecture notes, lab exercises and examinations and a list of textbooks used in his Medical School courses. Courses include anatomy, bacteriology, obstetrics and gynecology, pathology, pharmacology, and physiology.
  - Class Lists (Box 1)
  - List of textbooks (Box 1)
  - Lecture and Laboratory Notes
    - Bacteriology, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Human Anatomy, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
    - Microscopical and Developmental Anatomy, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Neuroanatomy, 1951 (Box 1)
    - Obstetrics/Gynecology (Box 1)
    - Pathology, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - Pathology Lab (Box 1)
    - Pharmacology, 1952-1953 (Box 1)
    - Physiology (Box 1)
    - Physiology Experiments, 1951 (Box 1)